<!-- $NetBSD: ap-ack.xml,v 1.22 2005/05/14 12:58:10 hubertf Exp $ -->

<appendix id="ap-ack">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>

  <para>The &os; Guide was originally written by Federico Lupi who managed
    the sources, coordinated updates, and merged all contributions on
    his own. Since then, it has been updated and maintained by the &os;
    www team. The Guide has progressed thanks to the contributions of many
    people who have volunteered their time and effort, supplied material
    and sent in suggestions and corrections.</para>

  <sect1 id="ap-ack-original">
    <title>Original acknowledgements</title>

    <para>Federico's original credits are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Paulo Aukar</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Grant Beattie, converted to XML DocBook.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Manolo De Santis, Audio Chapter</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Eric Delcamp, Boot Floppies</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Hubert Feyrer, who contributed the Introduction to TCP/IP
  	Networking in <xref linkend="chap-net-intro" /> including Next
  	generation Internet protocol - IPv6 and the section on
  	getting IPv6 Connectivity &amp; Transition via 6to4 in <xref
  	linkend="chap-net-misc-ipv6-6to4" />. He also helped with the
  	SGML to XML transition.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Jason R. Fink</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Daniel de Kok, audio and linux chapters fixes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Reinoud Koornstra, CVS chapter and rebuilding
	  <filename>/dev</filename> in the Misc chapter.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Brian A. Seklecki <email>lavalamp@burghcom.com</email> who
          contributed the CCD Chapter.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guillain Seuillot</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Martti Kuparinen, RAIDframe documentation.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>David Magda</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="ap-ack-current">
    <title>Current acknowledgements</title>

    <para>This document is currently maintained by the &os; www team.
      Thanks to their efforts, the document is kept up to date
      and available online at all times.
      In addition, special thanks go to (in alphabetical order):</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Hubert Feyrer, for getting the guide up to speed for
	  &os; 2.0, and for making numerous improvements to all
	  chapters.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Jason R. Fink, for maintaining this document and integrating
	  changes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Andreas Hallman, for his information in
	  <xref linkend="chap-net-misc-ipv6-6to4-ipf" />.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Daniel de Kok, for constant contributions of new chapters,
	  maintenance of existing chapters and his translation work.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Hiroki Sato, for allowing us to build PDF and PS versions of
	  this document.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Jan Schaumann, for maintenance work and www/htdocs
	  managment.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Lubomir Sedlacik, for some details on using CGD for
          swap in <xref linkend="chap-cgd-suggestions" />.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Dag-Erling Sm&oslash;rgrav, for the article on
	  <xref linkend="chap-pam" />.
	  See <xref linkend="ap-ack-licenses-pam" /> for the license
	  accompanying license.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Florian St&ouml;hr, for <xref linkend="cryptocds"
          />.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="ap-ack-licenses">
    <title>Licenses</title>

    <sect2 id="ap-ack-licenses-flupi">
    <title>Federico Lupi's original license of this guide</title>

    <para>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
      modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions
      are met:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
          notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
          notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the
          documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>All advertising materials mentioning features or use of this software
          must display the following acknowledgement:
          This product includes software developed by Federico Lupi for
          the &os; Project.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The name of the author may not be used to endorse or promote products
          derived from this software without specific prior written permission.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE AUTHOR <quote>AS IS</quote> AND
      ANY EXPRESS OR
      IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES
      OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED.
      IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT,
      INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT
      NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE,
      DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY
      THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
      (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF
      THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="ap-ack-licenses-pam">
      <title>Networks Associates Technology's license on the PAM article</title>


      <literallayout>Copyright (c) 2001-2003 Networks Associates Technology, Inc.
All rights reserved.

This software was developed for the FreeBSD Project by ThinkSec AS and
Network Associates Laboratories, the Security Research Division of
Network Associates, Inc.  under DARPA/SPAWAR contract N66001-01-C-8035
("CBOSS"), as part of the DARPA CHATS research program.

Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions
are met:
1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
   notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
   notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the
   documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
3. The name of the author may not be used to endorse or promote
   products derived from this software without specific prior written
   permission.

THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE AUTHOR AND CONTRIBUTORS ``AS IS'' AND
ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE
ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE
FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS
OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION)
HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT
LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY
OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF
SUCH DAMAGE.</literallayout>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</appendix>
